In this screencast we have a repository visualization image on the right, showing its structure and all its commits.
To see it in a real life, one usually use visualisation utilities or "git log" command.
Executing... and heres a detailed information on every commit.
Let me use the "--oneline" flag to make the output more concise.
By default "git log" outputs the commits starting from "HEAD".
По умолчанию git log выводит коммиты, начиная от HEAD.
But one can specify any other commit as id or a reference.
For example "git log master" displays the commits from the "master" branch, in our case these first three.
The "git log" command has many keys and features, which we are going to examine during the next several issues of our screencast.
When we know the commit we are interested in, we can have a look at it in more details, using the "git show" command.
The "HEAD" commit will be shown by default.
But one can provide any other as well, for example via the link to identifier.
As you see, here is a general commit info followed by the changes made.
Most of the time we are interested in commits that are one or two steps behind us,
or in some other link we are interested in.
To avoid dealing with identifiers, there is a special convenient syntax in git logs.
Its enough to add the "~" sign to get from any commit or link to its parent.
I mean like that ("git show HEAD~") - this is the commit,
the parent of a commit to which HEAD is pointing.
As you see, the output is the same as if we used the identifier.
If you put 2 tildes, then its its parent - so below.
Lets add a "--quiet" flag for brewity, so that it only show the information without the changes.
Three tildes is the commit below and so on.
Of course many tildes is not something one will write, therefore one can use a number to state number of tildes.
Three tildes is same as like that: "~3" - 3 commits behind.
Two tildes is same as like that "~2".
One doesnt mean anything, same as just a single tilde.
The word "HEAD" itself can be shortened by writing an atsign instead of it, like that "@".
Similar shorthand is used in git for "HEAD" only as "HEAD" is used way too often.
The only problem is that in windows powershell "@" - is a special symbol, therefore we need to wrap it into quotes.
But in the other shells it will work just fine as it is.
Also "HEAD" is not the only thing to which tilde can be added, but to any identifier or link to commit.
For example "master~" - one steps behind the "master", its same as 3 steps behind the "HEAD".
This output shows the difference between the files. But how can we check the whole files, not the changes only?
From previous issues we already know that "git checkout" command allows us to restore the file
at any commit time, e.g. say restore the index.html file of the parent commit.
But the result of this call will be the substitution of our current index.html file to its older version.
And this is not convenient, especially if we made any changes, as they will be removed.
And what if we dont want to change the current file, but want to see its old content instead?
"git show" can help us with that. For that after commit we have to specify a colon prefixed path.
Done, heres an index.html from the parent commit.
Of course we can specify any other commit or link.
E.g. lets have a look at the index.html in the corresponding peak of the "fix" branch.
And, finally lets have a look at the file version not from commit itself, but from the currently indexed version,
by adding a colon, but removing the commit in front of it, like that ":index.html".
This, of course, makes sense only in a case if the file version in the index differs to our current one.
This happens when we worked, indexed the changes and then changed something else in the file.
Like that we'll see the one that is in the index, I mean the version that will be saved with the next commit.
So, we had a look at the general history of the development same as previous versions of the files.
Also we got familiar with the access to the parent commits via tilde syntax.
There is another way to get access to commit, when we dont know its identifier( these are, actually, rarely remembered by anyone ),
but know that theres a word in description, like name of the function.
It looks like that: ":/" and thenthe thing we are looking for.
You can specify several words, by wrapping it all into quotes or regexp
But most of the time the specific word is being looked for.
By that git will find the latest commit with this word in its description, in our case here it is.
Lets note that this commit is not from the current branch.
For this syntax the branch doesn't matter, its just looking for the newest commit with this word in its description.
So this syntax was created to give access to the recent commits.
Of course this is not for the use in "git show" only, but in any other git command.
But if you want to find all the commits with such a word in the description or interested in anything more complex,
lets say look for commits that are changing some file or a function in a file,
then its also possible, but by using different flags of the "git log" command.
You can learn about it in more details in the issue on this topic.